<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?><feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" ><generator uri="https://jekyllrb.com/" version="4.4.1">Jekyll</generator><link href="/feed.xml" rel="self" type="application/atom+xml" /><link href="/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" /><updated>2025-07-16T14:17:21+00:00</updated><id>/feed.xml</id><title type="html">CalyxOS</title><subtitle>CalyxOS</subtitle><entry><title type="html">Community update - our progress on CalyxOS after the release of Android 16</title><link href="/news/2025/06/26/community-update-android-16/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Community update - our progress on CalyxOS after the release of Android 16" /><published>2025-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-26T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/news/2025/06/26/community-update-android-16</id><content type="html" xml:base="/news/2025/06/26/community-update-android-16/"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li>We have analyzed the potential impact on CalyxOS that the release of Android 16 will have, and the future trends it may be imply.</li>
  <li>Given the upstream changes and internal needs, the CalyxOS team is revising our development methodologies and processes for secure and streamlined future updates.</li>
  <li>In the last two weeks, we have made significant progress in building and running Android 16 on Pixel 6 and newer Pixels.</li>
  <li>We are working to bring up the rest of modern Pixels before shifting focus to Motorola and Fairphone devices.</li>
</ul>

<p>As we shared in our <a href="https://calyxos.org/news/2025/06/11/android-16-plans/">previous announcement</a>, the biggest change Google made with the release of Android 16 to AOSP was to not release the Pixel device configuration sources (device trees) and its driver binaries. Because Google has been leading the development of AOSP, this move not only means that Google’s internal development progress will further impact the timelines of custom Android distributions (ROMs), but also indicates that what has previously been open to the entire free and open-source software (FOSS) community is slowly and gradually being closed.</p>

<h3 id="what-it-means-to-calyxos-future-plans">What it means to CalyxOS future plans</h3>

<p>For developing CalyxOS (and other peer custom Android ROMs) on a variety of devices, there are three key elements to ensure coherent and consistent maintenance: device kernels, device trees, and the proprietary binaries used for different components of the system. In the past, releases of Android versions usually included Pixel device trees in AOSP or otherwise made them available for download. This allowed custom Android ROM developers to easily identify the configurations Google made in new Android versions and customize them accordingly. Starting with the Android 16 release, FOSS custom ROM developers will need to build and maintain their own device trees for Pixels, which takes a lot of guesswork and reverse engineering. Comparing code changes and finding ways around proprietary codes will be a major burden in all future updates.</p>

<p>However, this impact is somewhat limited on CalyxOS. A key factor in our resilience is that CalyxOS has been supporting devices from a diverse range of phone makers besides the Google Pixels — such as Motorolas, Fairphones, and SHIFTphones — which helps us adapt to device-specific development processes and code availabilities. Furthermore, our testing has been focusing on replicating real world experience seamlessly in our development process and we will continue this effort.</p>

<p>With this trend, we are also anticipating more changes in Android 16 QPR1 or QPR2 that could potentially impact kernels — there could be features that existing device kernels are not compatible with and will require significant work to continue to support past each of these AOSP updates.</p>

<p>The trend of Google’s gradual privatization of Android OS development, albeit challenging to all custom ROM developers, has drawn attention to the importance and efficiency of tools, methodologies and processes in each stage of the development, signing and release, especially when it is happening across 20+ devices on a regular cadence, and respects the significance of quick security updates. This most recent change has prompted a close look into our current workflow. Concurrently, we are conducting a series of serious internal reprioritizations, including development (cleaning device trees, automating the extracting and matching stock properties and policies), release (preparing to make it easier for future updates), and key signing (reinforcing and ensuring key integrity, resilience, audibility, and a secure chain of trust). As a result, our users will see a hiatus in our usual schedule with respect to security and general updates. We sincerely apologize for the impact this hiatus has on users of CalyxOS, but we believe this overhaul is vital to ensuring we can put our best efforts into protecting the privacy and digital security of people who trust us by using and contributing to CalyxOS.</p>

<h3 id="what-people-should-know-with-devices-we-currently-support">What people should know with devices we currently support</h3>

<h4 id="pixels">Pixels</h4>

<h5 id="modern-pixels">Modern Pixels</h5>
<p>We have made significant progress bringing up Android 16 on all currently supported modern Pixels with GS201/GS101 chips (Pixel 6 and later models). We are cleaning up the Pixel device trees to make them easier to mantain and update in the future. Support is planned to continue despite the changes introduced by Google in Android 16. Update dates in the near future will be delayed as we adjust and improve our processes to build a sustainable and secure pipeline.</p>

<h5 id="extended-support-pixels">Extended support Pixels</h5>
<p>Pixel devices in our <a href="https://calyxos.org/docs/guide/device-support/" target="_blank">extended support category</a> will be evaluated after mainline Android 16 work is done. We will share more details once we complete the assessment of the possible kernel backport work required in the near future and feature compatibility.</p>

<h4 id="motorola-fairphone">Motorola, Fairphone</h4>
<p>We are currently focused on completing our Android 16 port to Pixel devices. Support timeline will be reviewed afterwards with updates to follow per model.</p>

<h3 id="looking-ahead">Looking ahead</h3>

<p>Our next step is to consolidate the schedule for ensuing updates and share it publicly, as is expected from our community. This will include adjusting timelines for Android 16 and security updates in the near future, between now and QPR1. If you are using CalyxOS with a device mentioned above, please stay tuned on our website for the update schedule. If you are looking to start using CalyxOS today, we recommend that you kindly wait for our next update. You can reach us in our <a href="https://calyxos.org/community/" target="_blank">community channels</a> for any specific questions about CalyxOS, Android 16 and our plan. We will strive to release timely updates on our progress and plan as we have them, to our website.</p>

<p>As part of our broader mission, the Calyx Institute and CalyxOS team is committed to providing privacy-respecting tools and resources, centering on CalyxOS, that are accessible and usable by people, even as the Android landscape continues to change.</p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[We have analyzed the potential impact on CalyxOS that the release of Android 16 will have, and the future trends it may be imply. Given the upstream changes and internal needs, the CalyxOS team is revising our development methodologies and processes for secure and streamlined future updates. In the last two weeks, we have made significant progress in building and running Android 16 on Pixel 6 and newer Pixels. We are working to bring up the rest of modern Pixels before shifting focus to Motorola and Fairphone devices.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Android 16 and Pixel Support</title><link href="/news/2025/06/11/android-16-plans/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Android 16 and Pixel Support" /><published>2025-06-11T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-11T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/news/2025/06/11/android-16-plans</id><content type="html" xml:base="/news/2025/06/11/android-16-plans/"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li>On June 10th, Google released Android 16 to AOSP - but without Pixel device-specific source code.</li>
  <li>This unexpected change impacts all custom Android ROM development, including CalyxOS.</li>
  <li>We’re adapting our plans and will share updates as development progresses.</li>
</ul>

<p>Google has released Android 16 to AOSP, but this year’s release is different in a significant way: none of the usual source code for Pixel phones has been made available. This impacts not only CalyxOS, but the entire custom Android ecosystem.</p>

<p>Here’s what we know so far.</p>

<h3 id="androids-release-model-today">Android’s release model today</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Google continues to build on the <strong>trunk-stable / quarterly platform release (QPR)</strong> model, which has evolved since Android 12.</li>
  <li>Instead of one big annual release, Android now rolls out larger and larger updates every quarter (QPRs), with features, UI changes, and improvements landing throughout the year.</li>
  <li>This model improves consistency but increases complexity—especially for downstream projects like CalyxOS. We’ve already started porting our changes to AOSP 16, but this cycle presents new challenges.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="why-android-16-is-different">Why Android 16 is different</h3>

<p>Android 16 was released to <a href="https://android.googlesource.com/platform/manifest/+/android-16.0.0_r1">AOSP</a> yesterday but with a one big difference than typical releases:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Google did not publish any device-specific source code for supported, modern Pixel devices.</strong></li>
  <li>In previous years, Google released full device trees alongside new Android versions. This allowed developers to build and boot AOSP on Pixel hardware relatively easily.</li>
  <li>With Android 16, only the platform/framework code has been released. The device trees are missing, at least for now.</li>
</ul>

<p>This means AOSP 16 cannot currently be built or run on any recent Pixel device easily just using official source. It’s unclear whether this is a delay or a policy change. Either way, it seriously disrupts custom ROM development and our porting efforts.</p>

<h3 id="calyxos-device-support-status">CalyxOS Device Support Status</h3>
<h4 id="pixel-6---9a">Pixel 6 - 9a</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Without official source code, these devices are currently unsupported for AOSP 16 builds.</li>
  <li>Pixel devices were widely supported in the custom ROM space due to their open-source friendliness (until now).</li>
  <li>We’ll need to approach them like other non-AOSP supported devices: with the GPL Linux kernel sources and updates to Android 15 device trees, which takes time and ongoing effort.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="fairphones-motorolas">Fairphones, Motorolas</h4>

<ul>
  <li>We’ll look into the status of Android 16 on these devices after we’re done with porting CalyxOS changes in general to AOSP 16</li>
  <li>We’ll post an update per device once we know more.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="pixel-5-series">Pixel 5 series</h4>

<ul>
  <li>We’ll look into the status of Android 16 at the end, and see what we can do, wrt extending support.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="references">References</h3>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://source.android.com/docs/setup/start">Building AOSP for Pixel Devices (Android 15 Guide)</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://android.googlesource.com/">AOSP Source code</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[On June 10th, Google released Android 16 to AOSP - but without Pixel device-specific source code. This unexpected change impacts all custom Android ROM development, including CalyxOS. We’re adapting our plans and will share updates as development progresses.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">June 2025 Security update</title><link href="/news/2025/06/09/june-security-update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="June 2025 Security update" /><published>2025-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/news/2025/06/09/june-security-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="/news/2025/06/09/june-security-update/"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li>CalyxOS 6.8.20 and 6.8.21 - Android 15 is now available for all supported devices</li>
  <li>June security update (2025-06-01)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="rollout">Rollout</h3>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Release channel</th>
      <th>Date</th>
      <th>Notes</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Security express</td>
      <td>6 June, Friday</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Beta</td>
      <td>6 June, Friday</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Stable</td>
      <td>9 June, Monday</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="changelog">Changelog</h3>
<ul>
  <li>CalyxOS 6.8.20 / 6.8.21</li>
  <li>Android 15</li>
  <li>June 2025 Security update (2025-06-01)</li>
  <li>Chromium: 137.0.7151.72</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="moto-g32">moto g32</h4>
<ul>
  <li>Revert recent brightness changes causing low brightness</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="note">Note</h2>

<div class="alert alert-info" style="margin-top: 3rem">
<ul>
  <li>
    <strong>Over-the-air Updates:</strong>
    [[CalyxOS updates =&gt; updates]] are delivered over-the-air (OTA) automatically, without any manual intervention needed. However, if you'd like to manually update your CalyxOS install, see [[OTA =&gt; ota]].
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Security Updates:</strong>
    The <strong>Pixel 9a, 9 Pro Fold, 9 Pro XL, 9 Pro, 9, 8a, 8 Pro, 8, Fold, Tablet, 7a, 7 Pro, 7, 6a, 6 Pro, 6</strong> contain the full security patch, as they are still being updated by Google.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Security Updates:</strong>
    The <strong>Fairphone 5, 4, Motorola moto g 5G - 2024, moto g84 5G, moto g34 and g45 5G</strong> stock OS follows a different security update release schedule, which usually lags behind by a month or two compared to Pixels. The CalyxOS releases for it only contain the latest fixes to the open source components, such as the OS code and the Linux kernel. Proprietary components such as the bootloader, modem firmware, and other firmware get updates as soon as the stock OS update is available.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>End-of-life:</strong>
    The <strong>Motorola moto g52, moto g42, moto g32, Pixel 5a (5G), 4a (5G), 5</strong> are no longer being updated by the manufacturer, so the CalyxOS releases for these devices only contain the fixes to the open source components, such as the OS code and the Linux kernel. Proprietary components such as the bootloader, modem firmware, and other firmware no longer get updates.
  </li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[CalyxOS 6.8.20 and 6.8.21 - Android 15 is now available for all supported devices June security update (2025-06-01)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Pixel 9a</title><link href="/news/2025/06/09/pixel-9a/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Pixel 9a" /><published>2025-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-06-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/news/2025/06/09/pixel-9a</id><content type="html" xml:base="/news/2025/06/09/pixel-9a/"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li>Google Pixel 9a is now officially supported by CalyxOS</li>
  <li>CalyxOS 6.8.10 - Android 15, QPR1, June 2025 Security update (2025-06-01)</li>
  <li>We welcome feedback at [[community]]</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="pixel-9a">Pixel 9a</h3>

<ul>
  <li>Some recently added CalyxOS features (<a href="https://calyxos.org/news/2025/04/25/april-feature-update/">April Feature update</a> and <a href="https://calyxos.org/news/2025/05/28/may-feature-update/">May Feature update</a>) will be unavailable,
because Google’s codebase for the Pixel 9a is older. As such, the Pixel 9a is on a different codebase than
our other supported devices, and is therefore missing some of the most recent changes.</li>
  <li>We’ve applied all relevant security patches, however, to ensure that the device remains secure.</li>
  <li>We anticipate bringing the Pixel 9a up to speed with latest features and Android 16 support in the near future.</li>
</ul>

<p>CalyxOS installation instructions available at [[tegu]].</p>

<h3 id="note">Note</h3>

<div class="alert alert-info" style="margin-top: 3rem">
<ul>
  <li>
    <strong>Over-the-air Updates:</strong>
    [[CalyxOS updates =&gt; updates]] are delivered over-the-air (OTA) automatically, without any manual intervention needed. However, if you'd like to manually update your CalyxOS install, see [[OTA =&gt; ota]].
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Security Updates:</strong>
    The <strong>Pixel 9a, 9 Pro Fold, 9 Pro XL, 9 Pro, 9, 8a, 8 Pro, 8, Fold, Tablet, 7a, 7 Pro, 7, 6a, 6 Pro, 6</strong> contain the full security patch, as they are still being updated by Google.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Security Updates:</strong>
    The <strong>Fairphone 5, 4, Motorola moto g 5G - 2024, moto g84 5G, moto g34 and g45 5G</strong> stock OS follows a different security update release schedule, which usually lags behind by a month or two compared to Pixels. The CalyxOS releases for it only contain the latest fixes to the open source components, such as the OS code and the Linux kernel. Proprietary components such as the bootloader, modem firmware, and other firmware get updates as soon as the stock OS update is available.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>End-of-life:</strong>
    The <strong>Motorola moto g52, moto g42, moto g32, Pixel 5a (5G), 4a (5G), 5</strong> are no longer being updated by the manufacturer, so the CalyxOS releases for these devices only contain the fixes to the open source components, such as the OS code and the Linux kernel. Proprietary components such as the bootloader, modem firmware, and other firmware no longer get updates.
  </li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Google Pixel 9a is now officially supported by CalyxOS CalyxOS 6.8.10 - Android 15, QPR1, June 2025 Security update (2025-06-01) We welcome feedback at [[community]]]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">May 2025 Feature update</title><link href="/news/2025/05/28/may-feature-update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="May 2025 Feature update" /><published>2025-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/news/2025/05/28/may-feature-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="/news/2025/05/28/may-feature-update/"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li>CalyxOS 6.7.23 - May 2025 Feature update for all supported devices</li>
  <li>Smaller update as we prepare for Android 16 with upstream release due next week</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="rollout">Rollout</h3>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Release channel</th>
      <th>Date</th>
      <th>Notes</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Beta</td>
      <td>23 May, Friday</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Security express</td>
      <td>27 May, Tuesday</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Stable</td>
      <td>28 May, Wednesday</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="changelog">Changelog</h3>
<ul>
  <li>CalyxOS 6.7.23</li>
  <li>May 2025 Feature update</li>
  <li>Seedvault:
    <ul>
      <li>Restart backed-up apps by default</li>
      <li>Reduced storage backup retention policy
        <ul>
          <li>7 daily, 4 weekly, 3 monthly, and 2 yearly storage backups are retained now</li>
        </ul>
      </li>
      <li>Removed file backup snapshots that can’t be decrypted</li>
      <li>Caught more exceptions to handle errors better</li>
    </ul>
  </li>
  <li>Fixed Microphone showing as “In use” indefinitely after prompted to unblock</li>
  <li>Fixed various settings for secondary users</li>
  <li>Chromium: 136.0.7103.125</li>
  <li>Updated all included apps</li>
  <li>Updated translations</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="note">Note</h2>

<div class="alert alert-info" style="margin-top: 3rem">
<ul>
  <li>
    <strong>Over-the-air Updates:</strong>
    [[CalyxOS updates =&gt; updates]] are delivered over-the-air (OTA) automatically, without any manual intervention needed. However, if you'd like to manually update your CalyxOS install, see [[OTA =&gt; ota]].
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Security Updates:</strong>
    The <strong>Pixel 9a, 9 Pro Fold, 9 Pro XL, 9 Pro, 9, 8a, 8 Pro, 8, Fold, Tablet, 7a, 7 Pro, 7, 6a, 6 Pro, 6</strong> contain the full security patch, as they are still being updated by Google.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Security Updates:</strong>
    The <strong>Fairphone 5, 4, Motorola moto g 5G - 2024, moto g84 5G, moto g34 and g45 5G</strong> stock OS follows a different security update release schedule, which usually lags behind by a month or two compared to Pixels. The CalyxOS releases for it only contain the latest fixes to the open source components, such as the OS code and the Linux kernel. Proprietary components such as the bootloader, modem firmware, and other firmware get updates as soon as the stock OS update is available.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>End-of-life:</strong>
    The <strong>Motorola moto g52, moto g42, moto g32, Pixel 5a (5G), 4a (5G), 5</strong> are no longer being updated by the manufacturer, so the CalyxOS releases for these devices only contain the fixes to the open source components, such as the OS code and the Linux kernel. Proprietary components such as the bootloader, modem firmware, and other firmware no longer get updates.
  </li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[CalyxOS 6.7.23 - May 2025 Feature update for all supported devices Smaller update as we prepare for Android 16 with upstream release due next week]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Four new Motorola devices added to CalyxOS support list</title><link href="/news/2025/05/28/new-motorola-device-support/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Four new Motorola devices added to CalyxOS support list" /><published>2025-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-28T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/news/2025/05/28/new-motorola-device-support</id><content type="html" xml:base="/news/2025/05/28/new-motorola-device-support/"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li>Four new devices, moto g 5G - 2024, g34 5G, g45 5G, g84 5G, are now on CalyxOS support list for Motorola phones</li>
  <li>We welcome feedback at [[community]]</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="why-these-devices">Why these devices</h4>

<p>Making CalyxOS accessible on diverse devices is always a priority at Calyx. Within our security standards, we keep trying to support as many devices as possible for as long as we can.</p>

<p>CalyxOS requires mobile devices to unlock and relock the bootloader securely during the flashing process to prevent unauthorized root access that can compromise these devices. Among manufacturers who allow secure bootloader unlock and relock, these four Motorola phones are relatively economical compared to other mobile devices, such as Pixel phones. They also have much wider global availability. You can find these models in countries across North America, Latin America, Europe, and Asia Pacific. Regional reach and affordability are both important to us.</p>

<p>Additionally, there was already some custom ROM development for these models, and we contributed to their official LineageOS port. That work helps provide the device and hardware specific code CalyxOS relies on.</p>

<h4 id="pre-install-notes">Pre-install notes</h4>

<h4 id="obtaining-an-unlock-code">Obtaining an unlock code</h4>

<p>Motorola requires you to request for a code to unlock the bootloader of these phones. For brand new devices, sometimes it may take up to 3 days before the phone will let you actually enable OEM unlocking. It can be instant or sooner than 3 days as well in many cases.</p>

<p>Do note that unlocking your Motorola voids it’s warranty.</p>

<p>The CalyxOS <code class="language-plaintext highlighter-rouge">device-flasher</code> currently does not handle this process, and thus you’ll have to manually unlock the device after obtaining the code.</p>

<p>In the future, we’ll try to automate as much of it as possible.</p>

<h4 id="unlock-code-link">Unlock code link</h4>

<p><a href="https://motorola-global-portal.custhelp.com/app/standalone/bootloader/unlock-your-device-a">https://motorola-global-portal.custhelp.com/app/standalone/bootloader/unlock-your-device-a</a></p>

<h4 id="moto-g-5g---2024">moto g 5G - 2024</h4>

<ul>
  <li>Please note, among moto g 5G phones, only the <a href="https://www.motorola.com/us/en/p/phones/moto-g/g-5g-gen-3/pmipmgl36mr">2024 model</a> is supported.</li>
  <li>Carrier-specific variants (e.g. Verizon, Tracfone, AT&amp;T, Cricket) may not allow bootloader unlocking and might be unsupported.</li>
</ul>

<p>Model-specific CalyxOS installation instructions available at [[fogo]].</p>

<h4 id="moto-g34-5g-and-moto-g45-5g">moto g34 5G and moto g45 5G</h4>

<ul>
  <li>These two devices share the same software.</li>
</ul>

<p>Model-specific CalyxOS installation instructions available at [[fogos]].</p>

<h4 id="moto-g84-5g">moto g84 5G</h4>

<p>Model-specific CalyxOS installation instructions available at [[bangkk]].</p>

<h3 id="note">Note</h3>

<div class="alert alert-info" style="margin-top: 3rem">
<ul>
  <li>
    <strong>Over-the-air Updates:</strong>
    [[CalyxOS updates =&gt; updates]] are delivered over-the-air (OTA) automatically, without any manual intervention needed. However, if you'd like to manually update your CalyxOS install, see [[OTA =&gt; ota]].
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Security Updates:</strong>
    The <strong>Pixel 9a, 9 Pro Fold, 9 Pro XL, 9 Pro, 9, 8a, 8 Pro, 8, Fold, Tablet, 7a, 7 Pro, 7, 6a, 6 Pro, 6</strong> contain the full security patch, as they are still being updated by Google.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Security Updates:</strong>
    The <strong>Fairphone 5, 4, Motorola moto g 5G - 2024, moto g84 5G, moto g34 and g45 5G</strong> stock OS follows a different security update release schedule, which usually lags behind by a month or two compared to Pixels. The CalyxOS releases for it only contain the latest fixes to the open source components, such as the OS code and the Linux kernel. Proprietary components such as the bootloader, modem firmware, and other firmware get updates as soon as the stock OS update is available.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>End-of-life:</strong>
    The <strong>Motorola moto g52, moto g42, moto g32, Pixel 5a (5G), 4a (5G), 5</strong> are no longer being updated by the manufacturer, so the CalyxOS releases for these devices only contain the fixes to the open source components, such as the OS code and the Linux kernel. Proprietary components such as the bootloader, modem firmware, and other firmware no longer get updates.
  </li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[Four new devices, moto g 5G - 2024, g34 5G, g45 5G, g84 5G, are now on CalyxOS support list for Motorola phones We welcome feedback at [[community]]]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Important notice regarding external storage bypass vulnerability</title><link href="/news/2025/05/21/external-storage-bypass/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Important notice regarding external storage bypass vulnerability" /><published>2025-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-21T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/news/2025/05/21/external-storage-bypass</id><content type="html" xml:base="/news/2025/05/21/external-storage-bypass/"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li>An AOSP security vulnerability allows third-party apps to bypass external storage restrictions and access sensitive folders without permissions.</li>
  <li>Google has received at least two reports of this issue, however, they have not released any public disclosure about status of the issue to this date.</li>
  <li>CalyxOS has released a fix to this issue with CalyxOS 6.6.22 and 6.6.23 in April 2025.</li>
</ul>

<h4 id="problem">Problem</h4>
<p>An Android Open Source Project (AOSP) security vulnerability was discovered that allowed third-party apps to bypass restrictions on the /sdcard/Android/data and /sdcard/Android/obb directories. By including “ignorable” Unicode characters (such as ‘\u200b’, a zero-width space) in the path, unauthorized apps could gain access to other apps’ external storage folders, which could lead to the exposure of sensitive information.</p>

<h4 id="impact">Impact</h4>
<p>The vulnerability allowed unauthorized discovery of installed apps and access to sensitive application data, which — depending on the apps’ design — could include location information, synchronization logs, and other files not intended for cross-app access. An app could use this vulnerability to explore these folders even without having any storage permissions.</p>

<h4 id="affected-devices">Affected devices</h4>
<p>This issue impacts AOSP-based devices with kernel versions 4.19 or greater, which includes all <a href="https://calyxos.org/docs/guide/device-support/">supported CalyxOS devices</a>.</p>

<h4 id="current-status">Current Status</h4>
<p>The vulnerability has been fixed in CalyxOS <a href="https://calyxos.org/news/2025/04/25/april-feature-update/">6.6.22 and 6.6.23</a>, released in April 2025. This update restores expected external storage restrictions and prevents unauthorized access via this bypass technique.
Earlier this year, the CalyxOS team was alerted to this issue by our community and learned that Google has been made aware of the vulnerability. While it remains unresolved in AOSP releases (and stock Google Android) as of the publishing of this news post, CalyxOS has released its own fix to ensure users are protected. The CalyxOS team is monitoring if this issue will be disclosed and resolved in AOSP in the near future.</p>

<h4 id="recommendation-for-affected-users">Recommendation for affected users</h4>
<p>We strongly recommend all users update to the latest CalyxOS release (6.6.22, 6.6.23 or newer) to ensure this vulnerability is mitigated. Devices running older versions remain vulnerable since potential exploitations do not need any storage access permission. 
As always, we recommend adhering to best practices for digital hygiene in general; restrict unnecessary app permissions, minimize sharing your senstive personal data with apps, and remove apps you don’t use. You can do this by exercising care when downloading apps to ensure they come from trusted sources, review individual app permissions periodically, stay cautious when you share personal data with apps, such as locations (with CalyxOS you can use <a href="https://calyxos.org/docs/guide/security/location/#strict-location-redaction">Strict Location Redaction</a> to minimize location data sharing across apps), accounts, and payment information, and remove apps you no longer need or use.</p>

<h4 id="next-steps">Next steps</h4>
<p>Individual users should update to the latest CalyxOS release (6.6.22, 6.6.23 or newer) to protect themselves against this vulnerability. The CalyxOS team will continue monitor the issue on AOSP as it remains undisclosed and unresolved by the Google team.</p>

<h4 id="gitlab-issue-link">GitLab Issue link</h4>
<p><a href="https://gitlab.com/CalyxOS/calyxos/-/issues/2848">https://gitlab.com/CalyxOS/calyxos/-/issues/2848</a></p>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An AOSP security vulnerability allows third-party apps to bypass external storage restrictions and access sensitive folders without permissions. Google has received at least two reports of this issue, however, they have not released any public disclosure about status of the issue to this date. CalyxOS has released a fix to this issue with CalyxOS 6.6.22 and 6.6.23 in April 2025.]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">May 2025 Security update - take two</title><link href="/news/2025/05/09/may-security-update2/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="May 2025 Security update - take two" /><published>2025-05-09T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-09T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/news/2025/05/09/may-security-update2</id><content type="html" xml:base="/news/2025/05/09/may-security-update2/"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li>CalyxOS 6.7.21-2 - Android 15 is now available for the FP5, FP4, Moto G32, G42, G52, Pixel 5a, 5, 4a (5G)</li>
  <li>May security update (2025-05-05)</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="rollout">Rollout</h3>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Release channel</th>
      <th>Date</th>
      <th>Notes</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Security express</td>
      <td>Friday, 9 May</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Beta</td>
      <td>Saturday, 10 May</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Stable</td>
      <td>Monday, 12 May</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="changelog">Changelog</h3>
<ul>
  <li>CalyxOS 6.7.21-2</li>
  <li>May 2025 Security update (2025-05-05)</li>
  <li>Chromium: 136.0.7103.60</li>
  <li>Update all included apps</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="note">Note</h2>

<div class="alert alert-info" style="margin-top: 3rem">
<ul>
  <li>
    <strong>Over-the-air Updates:</strong>
    [[CalyxOS updates =&gt; updates]] are delivered over-the-air (OTA) automatically, without any manual intervention needed. However, if you'd like to manually update your CalyxOS install, see [[OTA =&gt; ota]].
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Security Updates:</strong>
    The <strong>Pixel 9a, 9 Pro Fold, 9 Pro XL, 9 Pro, 9, 8a, 8 Pro, 8, Fold, Tablet, 7a, 7 Pro, 7, 6a, 6 Pro, 6</strong> contain the full security patch, as they are still being updated by Google.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Security Updates:</strong>
    The <strong>Fairphone 5, 4, Motorola moto g 5G - 2024, moto g84 5G, moto g34 and g45 5G</strong> stock OS follows a different security update release schedule, which usually lags behind by a month or two compared to Pixels. The CalyxOS releases for it only contain the latest fixes to the open source components, such as the OS code and the Linux kernel. Proprietary components such as the bootloader, modem firmware, and other firmware get updates as soon as the stock OS update is available.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>End-of-life:</strong>
    The <strong>Motorola moto g52, moto g42, moto g32, Pixel 5a (5G), 4a (5G), 5</strong> are no longer being updated by the manufacturer, so the CalyxOS releases for these devices only contain the fixes to the open source components, such as the OS code and the Linux kernel. Proprietary components such as the bootloader, modem firmware, and other firmware no longer get updates.
  </li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[CalyxOS 6.7.21-2 - Android 15 is now available for the FP5, FP4, Moto G32, G42, G52, Pixel 5a, 5, 4a (5G) May security update (2025-05-05)]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">May 2025 Security update - Pixel 6 - 9</title><link href="/news/2025/05/07/may-security-update/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="May 2025 Security update - Pixel 6 - 9" /><published>2025-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-07T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/news/2025/05/07/may-security-update</id><content type="html" xml:base="/news/2025/05/07/may-security-update/"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li>CalyxOS 6.7.20 - Android 15 is now available for Pixel 6 - 9 devices</li>
  <li>May security update (2025-05-05)</li>
  <li>IMPORTANT: Certain Pixel devices won’t be able to downgrade after this update</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="key-google-pixel-updates">KEY Google Pixel updates</h3>
<ul>
  <li>Google’s May 2025 Pixel update for Pixel 6 (6, 6 Pro, 6a) and Pixel 8 (8, 8 Pro, 8a) devices incremented the anti-roll back version for the bootloader.</li>
  <li>This prevents the above devices from rolling back to previous vulnerable versions of the bootloader.</li>
  <li>Once you flash the May 2025 update on these devices, you won’t be able to flash and boot older Android 15 builds.</li>
  <li>That update affects CalyxOS, Stock Android OS, and all other Android distributions.</li>
  <li>Trying to downgrade after this update may fail and make your phone unbootable.</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="rollout">Rollout</h3>

<table>
  <thead>
    <tr>
      <th>Release channel</th>
      <th>Date</th>
      <th>Notes</th>
    </tr>
  </thead>
  <tbody>
    <tr>
      <td>Security express</td>
      <td>7 May, Wednesday</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Beta</td>
      <td>8 May, Thursday</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
    <tr>
      <td>Stable</td>
      <td>12 May, Monday</td>
      <td> </td>
    </tr>
  </tbody>
</table>

<h3 id="changelog">Changelog</h3>
<ul>
  <li>CalyxOS 6.7.20</li>
  <li>May 2025 Security update (2025-05-05)</li>
  <li>Chromium: 136.0.7103.60</li>
  <li>Update all included apps</li>
</ul>

<h2 id="note">Note</h2>

<div class="alert alert-info" style="margin-top: 3rem">
<ul>
  <li>
    <strong>Over-the-air Updates:</strong>
    [[CalyxOS updates =&gt; updates]] are delivered over-the-air (OTA) automatically, without any manual intervention needed. However, if you'd like to manually update your CalyxOS install, see [[OTA =&gt; ota]].
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Security Updates:</strong>
    The <strong>Pixel 9a, 9 Pro Fold, 9 Pro XL, 9 Pro, 9, 8a, 8 Pro, 8, Fold, Tablet, 7a, 7 Pro, 7, 6a, 6 Pro, 6</strong> contain the full security patch, as they are still being updated by Google.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>Security Updates:</strong>
    The <strong>Fairphone 5, 4, Motorola moto g 5G - 2024, moto g84 5G, moto g34 and g45 5G</strong> stock OS follows a different security update release schedule, which usually lags behind by a month or two compared to Pixels. The CalyxOS releases for it only contain the latest fixes to the open source components, such as the OS code and the Linux kernel. Proprietary components such as the bootloader, modem firmware, and other firmware get updates as soon as the stock OS update is available.
  </li>
  <li>
    <strong>End-of-life:</strong>
    The <strong>Motorola moto g52, moto g42, moto g32, Pixel 5a (5G), 4a (5G), 5</strong> are no longer being updated by the manufacturer, so the CalyxOS releases for these devices only contain the fixes to the open source components, such as the OS code and the Linux kernel. Proprietary components such as the bootloader, modem firmware, and other firmware no longer get updates.
  </li>
</ul>
</div>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[CalyxOS 6.7.20 - Android 15 is now available for Pixel 6 - 9 devices May security update (2025-05-05) IMPORTANT: Certain Pixel devices won’t be able to downgrade after this update]]></summary></entry><entry><title type="html">Why we are phasing out the Cleartext Restriction feature</title><link href="/news/2025/05/06/cleartext-restriction/" rel="alternate" type="text/html" title="Why we are phasing out the Cleartext Restriction feature" /><published>2025-05-06T00:00:00+00:00</published><updated>2025-05-06T00:00:00+00:00</updated><id>/news/2025/05/06/cleartext-restriction</id><content type="html" xml:base="/news/2025/05/06/cleartext-restriction/"><![CDATA[<ul>
  <li>An in-depth explanation of our decision to retire the “Restrict cleartext network traffic” feature</li>
  <li>Next steps for users who are using this feature</li>
</ul>

<h3 id="overview">Overview</h3>

<p>The “Restrict cleartext network traffic” setting was introduced in CalyxOS as <a href="/news/2021/04/08/big-april-update/" target="_blank">an additional layer of protection</a>,
aimed to block cleartext transmission. Cleartext transmission allows data to travel in network or communication channels without encrpytion or other protection layers.
It can occur in various types of communications, such as visiting a website, sending an email, or sharing a file.
Cleartext transmission sends data in plain, human-readable format, making it easier for unauthorized parties to read sensitive information, such as password, personal data, or private messages.
Therefore, we bulit this feature on AOSP’s existing functionality in 2021 to improve overall device data security.
However, upon review, we have discovered that this feature bears significant limitations and usability concerns.</p>

<h3 id="what-we-learned--why-we-made-this-decision">What we learned // Why we made this decision</h3>

<p>After investigating issues <a href="https://gitlab.com/CalyxOS/calyxos/-/issues/1948" target="_blank">#1948</a> and <a href="https://gitlab.com/CalyxOS/calyxos/-/issues/2521" target="_blank">#2521</a>,
 our finding shows that AOSP’s cleartext restriction is not a comprehensive security mechanism.
It only inspects initial packets of a connection; once Transport Layer Security (TLS) is detected, the connection will beis marked secure, and there will be no further inspection.
An app could begin sending cleartext after the initial handshake without detection.
AOSP explicitly states that this feature is meant to prevent accidental cleartext traffic, not deliberate bypasses.</p>

<p>In addition to AOSP’s functional limitations, this feature created usability problems by conflicting with other features and services, such as:</p>
<ul>
  <li><strong>Blocking DNS-over-HTTPS (DoH) protocol</strong>: Private DNS setups using Cloudflare or Google failed silently.</li>
  <li><strong>Breaking QUIC traffic</strong>: Many modern apps rely on QUIC protocol to transmit data. Despite the fact that QUIC traffic was encrypted by default, it was blocked.</li>
  <li><strong>Interfering with VPNs</strong>: Some VPN traffic got misclassified as cleartext and blocked, affecting connectivity.</li>
</ul>

<p>Given these problems, continuing to maintain a “best-effort” solution, one that users might mistakenly assume is fully secure,
 risks giving a false sense of protection while breaking access to other secure services and connection protocols.</p>

<h3 id="whats-next">What’s next</h3>

<p>We have already started transitioning users away from this feature:</p>
<ul>
  <li>In the February CalyxOS Feature update, users who had this feature enabled received a one-time notification on their device alerting them that the feature would be removed in a future update.</li>
  <li>In the April CalyxOS Feature update, users who still have this feature enabled will again receive a notification (linking here) informing them that it has been removed.</li>
</ul>

<p>Instead of relying on this inadequate feature, you can use a VPN to protect your device’s connection and data transmission.</p>

<p>Additionally, we will continue to improve our communications about CalyxOS’ security and privacy features to ensure our users can make informed decisions and are aware of the best options for keeping their device secure and private.</p>

<h3 id="related-gitlab-issues">Related GitLab issues</h3>
<ul>
  <li><a href="https://gitlab.com/CalyxOS/calyxos/-/issues/1948" target="_blank">#1948</a></li>
  <li><a href="https://gitlab.com/CalyxOS/calyxos/-/issues/2521" target="_blank">#2521</a></li>
</ul>]]></content><author><name></name></author><summary type="html"><![CDATA[An in-depth explanation of our decision to retire the “Restrict cleartext network traffic” feature Next steps for users who are using this feature]]></summary></entry></feed>